MADHU DEVARAJ

linkedin.com/in/madhudevaraj | github.com/madhudevaraj | (201) 208-4424 | madhusdevaraj@gmail.com

SUMMARY

Software Engineer with **3 years** of professional experience in software development phases including requirement analysis, design, development and QA automation testing. I am currently pursuing Masters in Computer Science with a focus on Full Stack Application Development and actively seeking full-time opportunities in Software Engineering.

EDUCATION

M.S, Computer Science, George Washington University, Washington DC (Expected May 2019) GPA - 3.78/4.0 Course Work: Database Management Systems, Design and Analysis of Algorithms, Object Oriented Programming, Big Data

B.E, Computer Science, Visvesvaraya Tech. University, Bangalore, India (2010 – 2014) GPA - 3.77/4.0 Course Work: Data Structures, Algorithms, Database, Software Engineering, Operating Systems, JAVA, Programming languages

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Languages / Technologies: JAVA, JavaScript, AWS Cloud, HTML 5, CSS 3, SQL, Angular 2, Bootstrap, Spring, Hibernate,

REST Web Services, Node.js MySQL, Oracle, MongoDB

QA Automation Technologies: JUnit, Selenium WebDriver, TestNG

Traile A COL Ward hards Cit Line Desferre Date

Tools: Eclipse, MySQL Workbench, Git, Jira, Perforce, Putty, Jenkins CI/CD

Operating System: Unix / Linux, Windows

Concepts: Strong Knowledge in Data Structures and Algorithm; Extensive experience in SDLC - Agile

Scrum Methodology and Object Oriented Programming.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE [3 years]

Software Engineer, Micro Focus, Washington D.C.

Databases / Servers:

May 2018 - Present

Project: ArcSight Command Center (Technologies: MongoDB, Express.js, Angular 2, Node.js, Mongoose, Passport)

- Built REST APIs to implement various functionalities using Node.js, Express, Mongoose. Performed token generation and authentication using Passport and JWT (JSON web tokens).
- Designed and developed front-end using Angular 2 along with Angular 2 flash message module and Angular 2-JWT module for authentication. Used MongoDB database and MongooseJS as Object Document Mapper (ODM).

Project: Enterprise Security Manager (Technologies: JAVA, Selenium, TestNG, Jenkins, Perforce, Jira)

- Designed and developed software automation test suites for Enterprise Security Manager application on a distributed system architecture using Java and Selenium WebDriver along with the use of TestNG annotations.
- Used Perforce for version control and integrated automation test suites on Jenkins for continuous integration (CI/CD).

Graduate Assistant, George Washington University

Aug 2017 - May 2018

• Worked under Associate Dean of Computer Science as graduate assistant for: JAVA, JavaScript, Relational Database Systems

Software Developer, Cognizant Technology Solutions, India

Aug 2014 - Oct 2016

Project: Akzonobel B2B application (Technologies: JAVA, SQL, Jenkins)

- Collaborated with the client to gather requirements and worked on JAVA based Integrated Development Environment.
- Developed and delivered a well-architected B2B application that processes hundreds of transactions per second and deployed it in a high-impact production environment.
- 80% of my time was spent in coding modules, developing enhancements, performing testing and debugging critical issues.
- Increased efficiency by 75% by improving the retry mechanism in production which led to reduction of failed transactions.
- Developed SQL queries to generate precise reports of failed transactions which helped in processing transactions efficiently.
 Project: Transit Website Development (Technologies: JAVA, Spring, Hibernate, Angular 2, JavaScript, MySQL)
- Developed transit application in a team of 4. Handled front end and worked on API based services that interacted with MySQL Database. Performed automation testing using Selenium and QF-Test, resulting in increased efficiency.

PROJECTS

Hand Gesture Recognition Algorithm [OpenCV, JavaScript, Node.js]

• Designed a hand gesture recognition algorithm which converts the gesture into binary mask, removes noise and computes convex hull of the hand contour to detect simple hand gestures.

iProtect - Image Recognition and Identification with Real-Time Alerts [PubNub, Python, JavaScript]

• Developed a real-time application to help users to keep tabs on their pets. User is alerted with an SMS to help protect their pets when a threat is detected. Made use of Google Cloud Vision API and PubNub.

IntelliBot - A Smart Chatbot [Javascript, JAVA, Bootstrap]

• Built a Chatbot which responds to user queries. User can interact with the bot via text or voice. The Chatbot has the ability to reply through both text and audio.

Budget App [JavaScript, HTML 5, CSS 3]

• Developed web application using "Module Pattern" design pattern. To obtain encapsulation/data-privacy used IIFEs and closure. Used the "separation of concerns" (SoC) design principle and used concepts of event delegation and event bubbling.

Dice Game [JavaScript, JQuery, HTML 5, CSS 3]

• Implemented a multi-player game "Pig Dice", a responsive web application using JavaScript. Used JQuery for dice animation, extensively used anonymous functions, performed DOM manipulation and used event listeners.

ACHIEVEMENTS

- Founder of 'Apti-LITe Sigma', a non-profit start-up where I taught Computer Science and Mathematics to about 300 undergrads.
- Was awarded 'Performer of the year' in Cognizant for 2015-16. Also, designated as Chief of University during bachelors.